참 재밌다
Arab League snow
?? has not seen your mother and the daddy
왜 너희 부모님이 안보이시지?
They very early not in
아침 일찍 나가셨어요
The father frequently very late only then comes back
Each time all drinks
아버지는 술에 취해서
늦게 돌아와요
Spits obtaining place all is, holds all holds motionless
그리고 아무 데나 토해서
부축할 수도 없어요
Your shop what time closes?
가게는 언제 문닫아?
In March
3월에요
Has the period of time is not very chaotic
한 때 아주 시끄러웠죠?
Also has died very many people
그 때 많은 사람이 죽고
The next door often is also copied
옆집에도 큰일이 생겨서
Father's friend Mr. Xu is also caught
아버지의 친구인 허선생님도
잡혀갔어요
Arab League snow
아설!
Aunt, uncle came back
언니, 삼촌이 왔어요
I have waited in the station for a long time
정류장에 오래 기다렸어요
I knew
He can that gate come out from the bridge
그쪽으로 올줄 알았어요
Arab League snow
아설, 이리 와 봐라
Is called the younger brother them to come back
예
Aunt, you slowly writes
천천히 쓰세요
Uncle this cannot eat
삼촌, 그건 먹으면 안돼요
For me
제사때 쓰는 거예요
This is must do obeisance the gods
Could not again eat
야위셨군요
건강은 괜찮아요?
오빠는 집을 나간 후
지금까지도 소식이 없어요
지난 번엔 많은 헌병들이
오빠를 찾으러 왔었어요
Wen Ch'ing... ...
문청!
Wen Ch'ing
오랜만이다
잘 있었어?
Mr. Huang came
오신다
Mr. Huang, this is my good friend
Wen Ch'ing
제 친구 문청입니다
He closes with your younger brother in same place
그는 선생님 동생과
Before your younger brother shoots
Said some speeches with him
같은 감옥에 있었는데
동생이 총살당하기 전에
한 말을 전해주러 온 겁니다
Therefore today especially comes to see you
Seat
태어나며 조국을 이별했고
죽어서 조국에 갑니다
생사는 하늘에 달린 것
슬퍼하지 마십시오
관영은 이미 결혼했는데
어디 있는지는 말할 수 없어
그가 나에게
집안식구들에게 말하지 말랬어
자신을 죽었다고 생각하래
그는 조국의 아름다운 미래에
몸을 바쳤다고 했어
난 감옥에서 친구와 같은
길을 가기로 맹세했어
그렇지 않으면 옛날처럼
생활할 수가 없어
난 여기 있고 싶어
너희가 하는 일을
나도 충분히 할 수 있어
여긴 네게 적합치 않아
나라를 사랑하는 마음이
변하지 않는다면
어느 곳에서 어떤 방식으로도
할 수가 있어
그리고 관미는 집에서
중매를 서려고 해
하지만 그녀는 네 것이야
이리 와
I have said with you
This is I best friend, the article is clear
내 친한 친구인 문청이야
The business also needs to do?
떠들지 말고 밖에 나가서 놀아
Do not be like this noisy
Outside exits plays
Arab League is good
This is must worship
그건 제사 음식이니
Does obeisance eats again...
제사가 끝나고 먹어
언제까지 가게를 닫을 거죠?
The business must stop, also is you says
Any time is open for business you also not to say
왜 말을 안해요?
묻는 말에 대답 좀 해요
Each time asks you, the smelly face did not say
어서요
Why not quickly decided?
조용히 해, 괜히 힘빼지마
You are crying
Talks incessantly
입대고 마시지 말아요
You do not want this appearance to drink
애들 교육에 안좋아요
Teaches people bad things the child
어른이 모범이 돼야죠
The such big person, has drunk tea also like this drinks
속이 타죠?
Has been able to be thirsty?
한꺼번에 많이 마시니까 그렇죠
Cannot drink do not have to drink such many
Smiled the person
Said you
이삼일동안 어디 갔었기에
Two three days see the person
Were you run to where go?
콧배기도 안보였냐?
하루종일 집에 있거나
Is not closes all day in Fang Li
Is everywhere runs all over the place
밖에 나가면 들어오질 않아
Let the others find
아침에 같이 어머니 묘에
Early morning wants to look for you goes mother in the grave to break off a relationship
Finds you
가려고 했는데 어디 갔었냐?
어머니는 우리 4형제를
No wonder throws all does not throw the victory to smile ?
You thought looked
Arab League homalium hainanensis four sons
낳고 기르셨어
그런데 나 혼자만 가면
Only sees my to go
He certainly can ask
당연히 물으실거야
네 얘기 좀 하자
I say along with to her listen
Talks about you
넌 계속 이렇게 살 거야?
You are not like this work all do not do
난 옆에 있는 사진관을
I planned opens in the next door
The photo studio manages for you
네게 맡길 생각이야
네 생각이 어떤지 말해봐
Said such for a long time with you
그래야 내가 결정하지
Good or is not good
You must say with me only then knew
그렇게 말하면 알아들어요?
You call him ?? to say
He hears
빌어먹을, 조용히 해!
Does your mother, peaceful
집에 오면 욕만 하고
Only knows scolds, comes back can verbal abuse
아설, 네가 말해봐라
The Arab League snow, you say to him listen
그녀는 체면불구하고
Others girl
우리 집에 왔어
In does not give a thought to the dignity to come home
무슨 뜻인지 충분히 알잖아
Any meaning already very much understood
Can't you really all look?
그런데도 넌 모르겠어?
네 속을 난 정말 모르겠다
You in do not fill any
I really do not understand
시끄러워!
Is crying, do not have to sing
빌어먹을, 조용히 해!
Does your mother
Peaceful
왜 노래를 부르고 난리야!
Sings any thing
Sings this any, sings bad luck
시끄럽다는데 왜 말을 안들어?
What roars? What roars?
왜 소리를 지르고 그래?
조용히 말로 하지
How should use to say
You shout and wrangle do?
왜 소리를 질러?
???
도대체 왜 그래?
Does not have the means, your this kind of person this kind of individuality
저런 사람의 성격은
귀신과 별 차이가 없어
미안하네, 왜 그런건가?
Sorry
Was a moment ago ???
모릅니다
Did not know... ...
저런 사람은 신경쓰지 말게
His this careless person, do not manage him
노래를 참 잘하는군
You sing are very good
고맙습니다
Do not manage him
그는 소와 같아서
This kind of person is same with the cow
가르칠 수가 없다네
Teaches not to be able to be teaches not to be able, does not have the means
신경쓰지 말고
어서 노래나 계속해
빌어먹을! 다 내 거야
어서 걸어
나도 걸었어
다 걸었지?
나쁜 자식!
Dry
너같은 놈이 아직 안죽었어?
Your this should die, but also has not died
문량은 너때문에 미쳤어
Arab League is good harmed by you well miserably
Deceased person
왜 쳐다봐? 어쩔 거야?
Does not know?
도대체 왜 그래?
You do?
What does?
왜 그러냐고?
모든게 너때문이야
Any matter you knew
말을 함부로 하는게 아니야
The thing may randomly eat
The speech may not randomly say
그러면 어쩔 거야?
How then you do have
두고 보자
How?
You suffice to plant
겁주는 거야?
You frighten the ghost
나쁜 자식, 언젠간 혼내주마
Your this small ?p three
Sooner or later will be doomed to have to die very much miserably
빌어먹을
모두 펴봐
형님! 형님!
Eldest brother
무슨 일이야?
??, Arab League fine?
아가, 왜 그래?
Quickly is called doctor
Or is important?
Kumchon, the knife receives
김전, 칼을 치워
가서 의사를 불러와
Quick, asks doctor to come
문웅!
Wen Hsiung!
신부가 와요
The bride came
신부를 모셔 와라
The bride bring in comes, to add Ding Chints'ai
복이 들어온다
절을 하세요
Worships
조상님께 일배
Does obeisance the ancestor
무릎을 꿇고
Kneels
절하세요
Does obeisance
일배
One kotow
이배
Two kotow
삼배
Three kotow
절하시고
Does obeisance
사배
Four kotow
오배
Five kotow
육배
Six kotow
절하시고
Does obeisance
칠배
Seven kotow
팔배
Eight kotow
구배
Nine kotow
일어나고
Gets up
맞절하세요
The father wife to does obeisance
꿇으시고
Kneels
서로의 사랑을 위해서
The father wife to does obeisance
Husbands and wives love
절하세요, 일배
One kotow
이배
Two kotow
삼배
Three kotow
일어나세요
Gets up
관미야
오늘 오후에 하늘에서
This afternoon
계속 천둥이 쳤다
Hears to the this year first spring thunder
마치 잠자는 산과 바다를
The monentum is very big,
깨우려는 듯
Like must all awaken Shan Kenhai general
아주 무섭게 쳤다
오후에 산에서 사람이 내려와
Afternoon in mountain some people
오빠가 돈이 필요하다고
Elder brother holds him to come clear to draw cash with the article
전해왔다
Said they need some funds
오늘은 국민들을 계몽시키려
Must print the thing, must educate the populace
인쇄물을 찍는다고 했다
또한 자주 문청에게
That person said
Frequently comes with the article clear to draw cash embarrassedly
손을 벌려서 미안하다고 했다
하지만 우리는 그들이
They did not know
We frequently are waiting for them to take
돈을 가지러 오면 기쁘다
그들이 돈을 가지러 온다는건
Because draws cash
We only then knew they have not all had the matter
안전하다는 뜻이기 때문이다
All also in is their ideal endeavor
We only then feel at ease
아겸은 어젯밤 젖을 먹이는데
Arab League was modest already could make noise
엄마라고 말을 했다
Last night held he ?? time
He looks like is being called mother
I am quite happy
난 너무 기뻐서
Runs is called the article clear to come in listens
문청에게 들으라고 했으나
Waits for me to see Wen Ch'ing
문청을 보는 순간 그가 듣지
Only then thought I am really stupid
How can he hear
못한다는 걸 알았다
하지만 문청이 듣지 못해도
The thing all is rising in prices
The neighbor all said the day does not feel better
난 서운하지 않다
문청은 말은 못하지만
Possible I to compare cannot think
아겸을 사랑하기 때문이다
Because I so long as see
Wen Ch'ingken Arab League modestly in side
Thought day very good, is very happy
편지 왔습니다
착하지?
거기 서! 서라!
꼼짝 마! 따라와!
가자, 빨리 가!
어딜 도망가? 거기 서!
Do not run!
빨리 도망가!
소리는 왜 질러?
조용히 못해? 일어나!
His mother, calls any to call
잡아
Seizes, seizes, seizes
모조리 잡아
무릎 꿇어, 빨리!
Kneels down
고개 숙여, 어서!
Lowers the head, lowers the head
고개 숙여
뭘봐? 가만히 있어
What does you?
숙여!
The Arab League snow, 4th oldest of father's ygr brothers is seized
아설, 삼촌이 잡혀갔는데
어디로 잡혀갔는지는 몰라
Which seizes, did not know to the present
우린 도망가려고 했지만
Initially we had thought must run away
더이상 갈 곳이 없었어
But, runs away again also has no way out
오늘에서야 편지를 쓰는 건
Only then writes a letter to today for you
마음이 안정됐기 때문이야
Is because the present mood only then quite is smooth
이 사진은 삼촌이 잡혀가기
This photograph is you 4th oldest of father's ygr brothers
Is seized previous three days to illuminate
3일 전에 찍은 거야
삼촌은 잡혀가던 날에
Is seized that day
사진현상을 하고 있었어
4th oldest of father's ygr brothers for person photography
그는 일을 다 끝내고서야
He persisted will work completes
조용히 그들을 따라갔어
Only then static is carried off
난 그를 찾으러 대북에
I go to Taibei to eavesdrop on in all directions
But all does not have the news
가봤지만 찾을 수가 없었어
아겸은 다 컸어
Arab League was modest already the long tooth
눈은 삼촌을 빼닮았어
Smiles the facial expression is very good
The eye likes very much 4th oldest of father's ygr brothers
언제 시간이 나면
In has spatially comes home
우리 집으로 놀러와
Nine started to transfer coldly
눈과 같이 하얀 아설에게
The awn flower opened
The full mountain misty white, likes the snow
치우고 밥먹자
Received, eats meal
알았어요, 곧 끝나요
Good, horse very good
애들이 도박하는 걸
Arab League wisdom
The child looks at any gambling sign with others
보면 안돼, 밥먹어
Leads uncle to eat meal
어서 식사해요
Uncle eats meal... ...
가자
밥 먹자
Uncle Wan?
곧 갈께요
He says as soon as discontinues comes back
빨리 와
알았어요
Was allowed to receive
많이 드세요
어서 밥먹자
1949년 12월
대륙은 공산화가 되고
국민정부는 대만으로 철수하여
임시수도를 대북으로 정했다